Preliminary Guide to the Paul M. Gross papers, 1939-1979 UA.05.53.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul M. Gross papers
1939-1979
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986
UA.05.53.0001
60 Linear Feet
Contains the personal and professional records of Paul Magnus Gross, a Duke University administrator, researcher, educator, and scholar. Gross was an Assistant Professor of Chemistry (1919-1920), William H. Pegram Professor of Chemistry (1920-1965), Chair of the Chemistry Department (1921-1948), Dean of the Graduate School (1947-1952), Dean of the University (1952-1958), and Vice-President in the Educational Division (1949-1960). The Paul M. Gross Chemistry Laboratory was named in his honor. Gross was also an independent consultant with the United States Army and various commercial companies. Types of materials include correspondence, clippings, reports, research papers, meeting notes, conference materials, contracts, speeches, dedications, eulogies, lecture notes, financial information, postcards, and building plans. Major subjects include Duke University, the Graduate School, the Department of Chemistry, University Council, the Board of Trustees, University Research Council, Duke University administration, University Committee on Long-Range Planning, Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies, study and teaching of physical sciences, military training, war education, munitions development, United States Navy, United States Army, Office of Ordnance Research, universities in the southern United States, and the Gross-Edens controversy. Major correspondents include J. Deryl Hart, Robert Lee Flowers, Douglas M. Knight, Marcus Hobbs, Charles E. Jordan, and Arthur Hollis Edens. Materials range in date from 1935-1979. English.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
Gift; 1993; A93-43 (Boxes 1-6, 10-27)
Gift; 1965; 65-122 (Boxes 7-9)
Gift; 1965; 65-28 (Boxes 28-42)
Transfer; 1986 (no accession number)
Biographical and Historical Note
Paul M. Gross was born in 1895. He received degrees from the City College of New York (B.S., 1916) and Columbia University (M.S., 1917 and Ph.D. 1919) in physical chemistry. He arrived at Trinity College in 1919, and began his tenure as Assistant Professor of Chemistry, teaching physical, organic, and fluorine chemistry. He led the Chemistry Department as Duke University underwent the transformation from regional college to research university. Gross served Duke University as an Assistant Professor of Chemistry (1919-1920), William H. Pegram Professor of Chemistry (1920-1965), Chair of the Chemistry Department (1921-1948), Dean of the Graduate School (1947-1952), Dean of the University (1952-1958), and Vice-President in the Educational Division (1949-1960). Gross was a proponent of scientific research and its value for education and society and held many seminars for science educators in North Carolina.
Gross directed Duke University's scientific research for both the U.S. Army and Navy during wartime. Naval Research on organic fluorine gases, compounds, and batteries was carried out by the Chemistry Department under contract with the Office of Naval Research. As part of the Army Scientific Advisory Panel, Gross advised top U.S. Army researchers on scientific matters. Gross was also involved in the Frangible Bullet Project, the largest military research project at Duke University. The frangible bullet, developed in 1942, was a plastic explosive that behaved like a bullet and enabled accurate training practices. The project earned Gross the President's Medal of Merit.
While a successful scientist, Gross is perhaps best known at Duke University as an administrator. Gross' administrative career at Duke University began in 1934 when he was named Chair of the University Research Council, a position he held until 1949. The Research Council helped to guide the University as it developed into a respected research institution. He also chaired the University Committee on Long Range Planning from 1959-1960. His opinions on administrative matters, along with his Vice President of Educational Division status, led to conflicts with President A. Hollis Edens around 1960, in what came to be known as the Gross-Edens Affair. The conflict mostly concerns the debate over whether Duke University should become a regional or national university, and to what degree the institution should be known for its devotion to research or teaching. Edens resigned from his position as University President, and Gross was removed from his administrative position as a result of the conflict.
In addition to his university positions, Paul Gross also served on numerous state, regional, and national boards relating to scientific research. In the late 1940s, he was a founder of the Oak Ridge Institute for Nuclear Studies (later Oak Ridge Associated Universities) and served as its President until 1949. President Harry S. Truman appointed Gross to the original National Science Foundation board in 1950, a position he held for 12 years. Gross held other administrative positions within the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the United States Health, Education, and Welfare Committee on Environmental Health, the Council of Southern Universities, the North Carolina Board of Science and Technology, Research Triangle Institute, Governor's Research Triangle Committee, and the North Carolina Atomic Energy Advisory Committee.
As an independent contractor, Gross was called upon to evaluate the composition of products including beer, cosmetics, film, and fire extinguishers. He was a sought-after speaker among his colleagues, giving many dedications, eulogies, lectures, panel discussions, testimonials, and dinner addresses during his career. When Gross retired from teaching at Duke University in 1965, the Gross Chemical Laboratory on Duke University's West Campus was named in his honor. Paul M. Gross died in 1986 at the age of 91.
Paul M. Gross was the son of Magnus and Ellen Sullivan Gross of New York. He married Gladys Cobb Peterson in 1918. They had two children: Paul M. Gross, Jr. and Beatrix Gross Ramey.
Collection Overview
Contains the personal and professional papers of Paul M. Gross. Gross served as a leader of many national scientific organizations. At Duke University, he was Assistant Professor of Chemistry (1919-1920), William H. Pegram Professor of Chemistry (1920-1965), Chair of the Chemistry Department (1921-1948), Dean of the Graduate School (1947-1952), Dean of the University (1952-1958), and Vice-President in the Educational Division (1949-1960). Types of materials include correspondence, clippings, reports, research papers, meeting notes, conference materials, contracts, speeches, dedications, eulogies, lecture notes, financial information, postcards, and building plans. Materials range in date from 1935-1979. Box 43 was added to the finding aid 8 March 2007 and is unprocessed.
Related Material
Duke University. President. Douglas M. Knight records, 1963-1969.
University Archives, Duke University.
Duke University. Office of the President. Robert Lee Flowers records, 1940-1948.
University Archives, Duke University.
Duke University. Office of the President. A. Hollis Edens records, 1949-1960.
University Archives, Duke University.
Duke University. Office of the President. J. Deryl Hart records, 1960-1962.
University Archives, Duke University.
Duke University. Department of Chemistry records.
University Archives, Duke University.
James R. Dean. Paul M. Gross: Leading the Good Against the Best, 1994 [904 D877 1994-DE]
University Archives, Duke University.
United States. Navy -- Artillery; United States. Army -- Artillery -- History; World War, 1939-1945 -- Education and the war; Chemistry -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Naval gunnery -- Technological innovations; Education, Higher -- Southern States; Education, Higher -- United States -- Administration; Education, Higher -- Aims and objectives; United States. Office of Naval Research; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Southern States; Ordnance, Naval -- Technological innovations -- United States; Duke University -- Administration; Council of Southern Universities, Inc. Southern Fellowships Fund; Duke University. Department of Chemistry; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Faculty; Flowers, Robert Lee; Duke University; Duke University. Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; Hobbs, Marcus E., 1909-; Hart, Deryl, 1894-1980; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986; Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-; Jordan, Charles E.; North Carolina Board of Science and Technology; Oak Ridge Associated Universities; Oak Ridge Institute of Nuclear Studies; Paul M. Gross Chemical Laboratory; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Faculty; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission
- Accession number: A93-43. 10-27
  - Speeches, 1945-1979 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Topics include the importance of graduate schools, specialization in science, and the environment. Includes addresses, dedications, eulogies, lectures, panel discussions, and retirement and testimonial dinner addresses.
  - Gross-Edens Controversy, clippings, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Speeches, 1945-1979 (Box 2)
    Topics include the importance of graduate schools, specialization in science, and the environment.
    - Addresses, dedications, eulogies, lectures, panel discussions, and retirement and testimonial dinner addresses. (Box 2)
  - Military Research: Budgets, July 1946-August 1949 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Duke University summary, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Supply Inventories, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Biographical Sketches, 1964; 1969 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Army Scientific Advisory Panel (ASAP) -- Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Secretary of the Army meeting, February 1964 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Fort Ord, CA, May 1964 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Washington DC, October 1964 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: AROD Durham, February 1965 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Fort Bragg NC, June 1965 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Detroit, Michigan, October 1965 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Fort Benning, GA, June 1966 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Army Science Conference, West Point, NY, June 1966 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Defense Center, Fort Bliss, TX, October-November 1966 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Washington DC, December 1966 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Natick Labs, Massachusetts, February 1967 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Electronics Command, Fort Monmouth, NJ, May 1967 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Aviation Material Labs, Fort Eustis, VA, October 1967 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Missile Command, Redstone Arsenal, AL, February 1968 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Joint Meeting Munitions Command, Dover, NJ, May 1968 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Edgewood Arsenal, Maryland, February 1969 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Fort Rucker, Alabama, May 1969 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Redstone Arsenal, Alabama, August 1969 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army Test and Evaluation Command, Aberdeen, Maryland, May 1970 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: Army Science Conference, West Point, NY, June 1970 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Meetings: US Army War College, Carlisle Barracks, PA, February 1973 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: ASAP: Newsletters (No. 1, 3-6, 8-9), 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Chemical Warfare Service: Mildewproofing: budget, correspondence, & progress reports, May 1946-July 1947 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Chemical Warfare Service: Mildewproofing: budget, correspondence, & progress reports, August 1947-July 1949 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Frangible Bullet: Correspondence: re: Army Truck, March - October 1945 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Frangible Bullet: Correspondence: Bakelite Corporation, Bloomfield, NJ, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Military Research: Frangible Bullet: Correspondence: Bell Aircraft Corporation, Buffalo, NY, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Frangible Bullet Project, 1941-1951 (Box 4)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Reports: Final report, 1945 December (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Meetings/conferences, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Reports, circa 1940s (Box 5)
  - Military research: National Defense Research Committee: Correspondence: Massachussetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Reports: Bakelite Corp. report to National Defense Research Committee, 1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Naval Research: Naval Research Laboratory: Correspondence, progress reports, and notes, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: National Defense Research Committee: Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Staff roster, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Supplies: Research equipment, 1944 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Supplies: Shipping orders, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Tables: Abbreviated firing tables, circa 1940s (Box 5)
  - Military research: Frangible bullet: Telephone conversations, 1943-1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Correspondence, 1963-1970 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: US Army Munitions Command, Danvers, NJ, 1964 March (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Frankford Arsenal, Philadelphia PA, 1964 May (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Edgewood Arsenal, NJ, 1964 August (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Fort Detrick, Frederick, MD, 1964 October (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1964 November (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Frankford Arsenal, Philadelphia PA, 1965 February (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1965 March (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1965 September/October (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Dust abatement, 1966 January (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1966 March (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1966 May (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Fort Detrick, Frederick, MD, 1966 October (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1966 November (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Fort Detrick, Frederick, MD, 1967 May (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1967 November (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Fort Detrick, Frederick, MD, 1968 November (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Meeting files: Munitions Command, Dover NJ, 1968 December (Box 5)
  - Military research: Munitions Advisory Group: Reference, circa 1960s (Box 5)
  - Military research: National Academy of Sciences: Ad Hoc Committee to Investigate Disposal Hazards of Certain Chemical Munitions, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Military research: National Defense Research Committee: Consultant correspondence, 1940-1945 (Box 5)
  - Military research: National Materials Advisory Board: Ad Hoc Committee on the Treatment and Disposal of High-Energy Materials and Related Components, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Military research: Naval Research: Battery cells: Annual reports, 1946 October - 1948 December (Box 5)
  - Military research: Naval Research: Battery cells: Progress reports, 1949 January-June (Box 5)
  - Military research: Naval Research: Battery cells: Correspondence and budget, 1946 April - 1950 January (Box 5)
  - Military research: Naval Research: Directions for keeping notebooks, circa 1940s (Box 5)
- Accession number: 65-122.
  - Military Research: Naval Research: Organic Fluorine Compounds: Annual Report (2 copies), October 1946 - September 1947 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Naval Research: Organic Fluorine Compounds: Progress Reports, October 1947 - June 1949 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Naval Research: Organic Fluorine Compounds: correspondence & budget, October 1947 - December 1951 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: O.O.R. Building (re: need for more space), 1957 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: O.O.R. Building dedication, 1959 May 14 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Correspondence: Col. W.W. Holler, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Meetings: Redstone Arsenal, Huntsville, AL, 1952 June 4-5 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Meetings: Junior Science Symposium, Chapel Hill, NC, 1958 May 7-9 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Meetings: Washington, DC, 1958 August 27-29 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Meetings: Diamond Ordnance, Fuse Laboratory, Washington, DC, 1960 July 28 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Meetings: Ordnance Corps Advisory Committee, Watertown, MA, 1961 November 6-7 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Proposal: Ordnance Institute of Chemical Physics, 1951 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Office of Ordnance Research, Durham: Research Reports (ARO-D), 1963 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Senior Scientific Steering Group: Meetings: White Sands, New Mexico, 1958 June 5-6 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Senior Scientific Steering Group: Meetings: Huntsville, AL, 1959 July 27-30 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Senior Scientific Steering Group: Meetings: ARO-Durham, 1965 November 2-3 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Senior Scientific Steering Group: Meetings: ARO-Durham, 1966 August 16-17 (Box 6)
  - Military Research: Senior Scientific Steering Group, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Bookplate (P.M.G.), circa 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
  - Personal: Consulting correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Consulting correspondence, 1939-1943 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1947 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1958 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Personal: Correspondence: Cosmos Club Nominations, 1967-1970 (Box 6)
  - Professional organizations, 1935-1979 (Box 7)
    Includes correspondence with some professional organizations, mostly American Chemical Society and UNESCO-related
  - Professional organizations, 1935-1979 (Box 8)
    Includes meeting notes, lectures, speeches, correspondence, reports, member lists, and general material regarding Gross and the American Chemical Society and UNESCO.
  - Professional organizations, 1935-1979 (Box 9)
    Includes meeting notes, lectures, speeches, correspondence, clippings, and reports of the National Science Foundation and the National Science, Board Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Science Committee
- Accssion number: A93-43
  - Professional organizations and endowments of Duke University, 1950-1979 (Box 10)
    - American Association of University Professors (1953-1956), reports, meeting notifications, clippings, correspondence (Box 10)
    - Association of Graduate Schools, reports, notes, correspondence, pamphlets, 1950-1958 (Box 10)
    - Criticism regarding Gross' retirement (Box 10)
    - Carnegie Corporation, correspondence, reports, applications, 1950-1953 (Box 10)
    - Rockefeller Foundation materials (Box 10)
    - Conference on Dean of Graduate Schools, Council of Southern Universities, 1969-1979 (Box 10)
  - Council of Southern Universities, general meeting notes, reports, and correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 11)
  - Professional Organizations (Box 12)
    - Southern Fellowship Fund, Executive Committee and Board of Director meeting notes. (Box 12)
    - Council of Southern Universities, general meeting notes (Box 12)
    - Ford Foundation Institute of International Education (Box 12)
      Includes grant proposals, reports on higher education funding, behavioral studies, and occupational retirement.
  - Graduate School, correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 13)
  - Graduate Council notes (Box 13)
  - Menhaden oil (in fisheries), studies, correspondence (Box 13)
  - Marine Laboratory studies and projects, proposals to National Science Foundation (Box 13)
  - Cooperative Research Vessel Program in Biological Oceanography (Box 13)
  - National Institute of Health meeting at Duke University, 1958 (Box 13)
  - President M. Toure of Guinea, 1959 (Box 13)
  - President's Reports, report of the VP in charge of the Educational Division, 1949-1959 (Box 13)
    Includes Arthur Hollis Edens correspondence
  - Professional organizations (Box 14)
    - President's Science Advisory Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 14)
    - Southern Association of College and Secondary Schools, 1949 (Box 14)
    - Southern Association of Science and Industry, Inc., 1949 (Box 14)
  - Southern University Conference, 1955 (Box 14)
  - U.S. Atomic Energy contract, teaching and study Atomic Energy in the South, 1956, meeting notes (Box 14)
  - Fallout preparedness at Duke University, seminar notes, schematics for buildings, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson fellowships, 1965-1966 (Box 14)
  - Office of Ordnance Research at Duke University, publications, research notes (Box 15)
  - Laboratory Conference for Science and Math Teachers, held at Duke University, 1954 (Box 15)
  - AAUP report "The Rights and Responsibilities of Universities and Their Faculties" (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and the U.S. Army (regarding environmental health) (Box 15)
  - Civil Defense (Box 15)
  - Lectures, Sigma Xi (1951) and memorial for Dr. F. London (1963) (Box 15)
  - Council on Aging (Box 15)
  - University Research Council Grant, 1961-1965 (Box 15)
  - Marine Laboratory in Beaufort, N.C (Box 15)
  - Accelerated Program at Duke University, 1942-1943 (Box 15)
  - Duke Council for American Defense University Defense Committee, 1941 (Box 16)
  - Research Associate material, 1960-1961 (Box 16)
  - Science Teachers Workshop, 1952 (Box 16)
  - Duke University N.A.S.A. Space Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 16)
  - Proposal for a space studies program at Duke University Duke Endowment, 1962-1968, meeting notes (Box 16)
  - "The Status and Needs of the Private University for Meeting the Task Ahead, with Special Reference to Graduate Education", author unknown, ca. 1960 (Box 16)
  - Aging Center plans, 1958 (Box 16)
  - Biology building, Zoology, Forestry, and Botany Departments, ca. 1956 (Box 16)